Guide to the Konstantin Reichardt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Konstantin Reichardt papers
1800-1988
1930-1976
MS 1619
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.75
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, writings, and research and teaching files which document Konstantin Reichardt's career as an expert in the study of Germanic philology and Scandinavian cultures. The correspondence is to and from family members, students, colleagues, publishers, and academic and cultural organizations. Topical files, which include genealogical studies of Reichardt's family and that of his wife, Patricia Barker Reichardt, are also included. The writings contain both published and unpublished works of Reichardt and selected writings of others. Research and teaching files consist primarily of Reichardt's handwritten notes on language and literature. The majority of these files are in Germanic, Scandinavian, Irish, and Sanskrit languages.
Reichardt, Konstantin, 1904-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Patricia Reichardt, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Konstantin Reichardt was born in St. Petersburg, Russia on April 30, 1904. In 1927 Reichardt received a Ph.D. from the University of Berlin. From 1926-1929 Reichardt taught Old Norse at the University of Berlin and in 1930 at the University of Cologne. In 1931 he became professor of North Germanic Languages and Literature at the University of Leipzig. Reichardt remained in this position until 1937 when the political climate in Nazi Germany prompted him to move to Sweden. In 1938 Reichardt was a Lecturer in German and Scandinavian languages at the University of Gothenburg before emigrating to the United States. Reichardt taught at the University of Minnesota in a number of positions. In 1947 Reichardt joined the faculty of Yale University as a full professor. Reichardt was the Director of Graduate Studies in Germanic Languages from 1962-1971. He was named Leavenworth Professor of Germanic Languages and Literature Emeritus in 1970. He died in New Haven, Connecticut on January 19, 1976.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, writings, and research and teaching files which document Konstantin Reichardt's career as an expert in the study of Germanic philology and Scandinavian cultures. The correspondence is to and from family members, students, colleagues, publishers, and academic and cultural organizations. Topical files, which include genealogical studies of Reichardt's family and that of his wife, Patricia Barker Reichardt, are also included. The writings contain both published and unpublished works of Reichardt and selected writings of others. Research and teaching files consist primarily of Reichardt's handwritten notes on language and literature. The majority of these files are in Germanic, Scandinavian, Irish, and Sanskrit languages.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, Topical Files, and Photographs, ca. 1800s-1988, n.d. II. Writings, 1941-1973, n.d. III. Research and Teaching Files, 1932-1975, n.d.
German philology; Germanic languages; Philology; Reichardt, Konstantin, 1904-; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, Topical Files, and Photographs, circa 1800s-1988 1930s-1976; Series I
  Arrangement
  The material in this series is filed by personal name, corporate name, or subject. File folders are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - A-D (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andersson, Theodore M., 1958, 1965-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beare [Robert], 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bertha [aunt], 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical/personal documents, 1930s-1968, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Happy Birthday poster (Box 10)
  - Bloch, Bernard, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bluhm, Heinz, 1957-1958, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book reviews, 1927-1936, 1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cassirer, Ernst, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cassirer, Toni, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - College of St. Thomas (Minnesota), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Columbia University, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conant, Jonathan B., 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Demetz, Peter, 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - E-G (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ebbinghaus, Ernst A., 1960-1964, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Edgerton, Eleanor, 1949, 1963-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Edgerton, Franklin, 1952-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Eulogies, obituaries, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grandmother?, 1937-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - H-K (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hammerich, Louis L., 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Henel, Heinrich, 1957-1960, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Konstantin Reichardt Fund, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - L-R (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters ofintroduction, 1957, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lopez, Roberto, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Marcus, Carl-David [second husband of Martha (Hilde) Mannstaedt-Reichardt], 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Memorabilia, 1965, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Nermin?, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Photographs [Leningrad, Moscow], undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pierson, George [speech in honor of Konstantin Reichardt], 1972 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Publishers, 1932-1938, 1953, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pusey, Nathan M., 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Ranevsky, Boris [uncle], 1940 April (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Reichardt, Adelheid [mother], 1937-1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Reichardt, E. [uncle], 1947 November (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Reichardt, Konstantin
    - Correspondence to wife and daughter, 1960, 1965 MayAug, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
    - Genealogy, family documents, Circa 1800s-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 42-44)
    - Festschrift and tabula correspondence, 1967-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Reichardt, Lilo [sister-in-law], 1949 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Reichardt, M. [uncle], 1947 September (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Reichardt, Maria [daughter Mia"], 1958?, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Reichardt, Patricia (Barker)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1953, 1957, 1965-1979, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Unidentified, 1977, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Letters of condolence, 1976-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 51-53)
    - Genealogy, family documents, 1894, 1927, 1943-1947, 1953, 1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Reichardt, Paula, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Reichardt, Robert [father], 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Reichardt, Waldemar [brother], 1938-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 57-58)
  - Richter, Werner, 1939, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - S-Z (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Scandinavian organizations, 1955, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Southern Connecticut State University, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Tau, Max, 1939, 1946, 1955-1960, 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - University of Minnesota, 1938-1948 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Verses, 1964, 1973-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Vikings [exhibition, British Museum], 1980 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Vinland Map
    - Conference, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Exhibition, 1967-1968, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Von Faber du Faur, Curt, 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Weigand, Hermann J., 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Wollert, E. (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Wood, Cecil, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Yale University
    - Appointments to faculty, professional correspondence, 1947-1974 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Correspondence in support of Reichardt's teaching appointment, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 75)
- Writings, 1941-1973; Series II
  The material in this series is filed chronologically by author.
  - Reichardt, Konstantin
    - Drafts
      - Holger Drachmann, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Henrik Wergeland and the Jews, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Camilla Collett, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Religious Life in Medieval Iceland, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - A Contribution to the Interpretation of Skaldic Poetry: Tmesis (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - "Islandische Geschichte" [IX: pages 407-487], undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - "Islendinga sogur" [X: pages 488-819], undated (Box 4, Folder 79-82)
      - "Konungasogur" [XI: pages 820-900], undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Published Works
      - "Altnordische Literatur als padagogischer Stoff, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - "Die Liebesbeschworung in For Skimis", 1939 (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - "From Pushkin to Tolstoy: An Advanced Russian Reader" [compiled by K. Reichardt], 1944 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - "Die Thorsdnlpa Des Eilifer Godrunarson Textinterpretation", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - "The Inscription on Helmet B of Negau", 1953 (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - "Medio Euo Negli Stati Uniti" [by K. Reichardt et al.], 1962 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      - Some Facts about Oral Tradition and Old Norse Literature" (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - "Beitrage zur Skaldemforschung I", undated (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - "Hymiskvida I", undated (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - "Odin am Galgen", undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Writings of others
    - "Der Skandinavische InfinitifAuf-U" [dissertation by G. S. Schtschur], 1959 (Box 4A, Folder 94)
    - "Sea Encounters," "Individual Combat," "The Burning" [Arthur Haase], 1967 (Box 4A, Folder 95)
    - "Public Oratory in the Old Norse Sagas" [prospectus for doctoral dissertation by James Knirk], 1972 June (Box 4A, Folder 96)
    - "The Origins ofthe Insular Celtic Conjunct and Absolute Verbal Endings" [Warren Cowgill], 1973 (Box 4A, Folder 97)
    - "An Essay on the Meaning and the Limits of Justification" [Herbert Feigl], undated (Box 4A, Folder 98)
    - "Germany in 1948" [unidentified author], undated (Box 4A, Folder 99)
    - Scandinavian mythology [typescript by unidentified author], undated (Box 4A, Folder 100)
- Research and Teaching Files, 1932-1975; Series III
  The material in this series is arranged with general files first, followed by specific folder titles in alphabetical order. "General" refers to materials which were received as loose, fragmentary, or unidentified papers.
  - General (Box 5, Folder 101-108)
  - General (Box 6, Folder 109-117)
  - After Tolstoy (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Celtic, substratum (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Danish literature (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Dream play (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Folkevise (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Garborg (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Gisli (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Glymdnipa (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Goncharov, Ivan (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Gothic nouns (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Goths (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Grammar (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - Hamsun (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Heroic poetry (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Hildebrand Legend, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Humanitie, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Husdrapa (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Ibsen (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Icelandic skalds (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Inversion accepted (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Jaeger, Hans (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Kjelland, A. (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Lie, Jonas (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - Menschenopfer (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Metrics (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Negau helmet inscription, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Norsk realism (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - Old Irish grammar (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - [Old Irisch/Deirdre?] (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - Old Norse (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - Renaissance (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - Runes: Kensington Stone, 1932, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 149)
  - Runic (Box 8, Folder 150)
  - Runic inscriptions (Box 8, Folder 151)
  - Runology, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 152-155)
  - Sanskrit (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - StentoftenIBjorketorp (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - Tmesis (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Tmesis rejected, vital statistics (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Tmesis type (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - Undset, Sigrid (Box 9, Folder 161)
  - Vellekla (Box 9, Folder 162)
  - Vinland Map
    - Newpaper clippings, 1967-1968, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 163)
    - Writings, historical background, 1951, 1965-1968, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 164)
  - Walde [Halo-Celtic] (Box 9, Folder 165)